<>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5008879105295771159.post-603423463787105866</id>
    <blogger:type>POST</blogger:type>
    <blogger:status>LIVE</blogger:status>
    <author>
      <name>dan.mackinnon</name>
      <blogger:type>BLOGGER</blogger:type>
    </author>
    <title>JUMP math</title>
    <content type='html'>&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjNIuieqHGtWEfZyv6umzTdydwmlcZw5BuYj757-G_-aVPHXGZXL9F8jCxDM6wCxLA0KEwBRRmT-Q17jOd_6t_MkgUC1JIvgkJ2TovCDptSI0HB6QTBkiRHJgDorc0vqNtd0SSPbVtWSOU/s1600-h/frank_kate2.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjNIuieqHGtWEfZyv6umzTdydwmlcZw5BuYj757-G_-aVPHXGZXL9F8jCxDM6wCxLA0KEwBRRmT-Q17jOd_6t_MkgUC1JIvgkJ2TovCDptSI0HB6QTBkiRHJgDorc0vqNtd0SSPbVtWSOU/s400/frank_kate2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: small;"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; image from &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=NAcAAAAAYAAJ"&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: small;"&gt;Everyday Number Stories&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A couple of years ago I saw a presentation by &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Mighton"&gt;John Mighton&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://jumpmath.org/"&gt;JUMP math&lt;/a&gt;. He is an interesting and engaging speaker, and you should check out &lt;a href="http://elementsofhumanity.com/#/video/entry/34/"&gt;his short video&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;at MAKE magazine's &lt;a href="http://elementsofhumanity.com/"&gt;The Elements of Humanity&lt;/a&gt;. An example of how a community organization has been able to implement the JUMP program can be found &lt;a href="http://www.ocri.ca/education/jump.asp"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, at the Ottawa Centre for Research and Innovation (OCRI) site.</content>
    <blogger:metaDescription/>
    <blogger:created>2009-10-29T15:17:09.689Z</blogger:created>
    <published>2009-10-29T15:23:00Z</published>
    <updated>2011-09-11T02:01:20.835Z</updated>
    <blogger:location/>
    <category scheme='tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5008879105295771159' term='math'/>
    <category scheme='tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5008879105295771159' term='school math'/>
    <blogger:filename>/2009/10/jump-math.html</blogger:filename>
    <link/>
    <enclosure/>
    <blogger:trashed/>
  UMP. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
4. John Mighton, JUMP's founder strongly believes that no one has an innate inability that prevents them from learning and enjoying mathematics. &lt;a href="http://mathrecreation.blogspot.com/2009/12/mathematical-nature-and-nurture.html"&gt;I agree&lt;/a&gt;, and I think sharing this assumption is a necessary starting point for anyone involved in teaching math to young people.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: large;"&gt;A bit more context:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
JUMP, having started as a tutoring program founded by an education-industry outsider is not always understood to be a complete classroom program, which it now is. Its charity status means that it threatens the big industry text-book publishers who, while promoting their own (for-profit) texts and resources, likely do their best to block JUMP from gaining any ground. JUMP's charity status has led it to adopt a business model where it offers its teacher-resources for free, and recoups costs through printing and selling workbooks (which they claim are not even necessary - the teacher resources are the main part of the program). As a charity, JUMP has not joined the text-book publishing business, and because it does not publish a bound textbook it is not fully sanctioned by Ontario's &lt;a href="http://www.curriculum.org/occ/trillium/resources/Mathematics_elementary.shtml"&gt;Trillium List&lt;/a&gt;. In addition to these barriers, JUMP has often been misunderstood, and sometimes misrepresented by its proponents, as a "back to basics" approach that is somehow at odds with current approaches in math education.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Seeing JUMP as "back to basics / skill and drill" approach to mathematics misunderstands its approach at a fundamental level. This misunderstanding has developed in part because of the workbooks (which at a quick glance look like a bunch of worksheets), and because JUMP is very task-oriented. Folks from JUMP take pains to point out that it does not emphasize drill, but instead "guided exploration" and "micro-inquiry" - the workbooks are supplementary, and shouldn't be looked at out of context from the teacher resources. Although the teacher is called up on to explicitly teach concepts, the lessons are set up so that students are continuously working on tasks, providing many opportunities for formative evaluation and feedback.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In this approach, numeracy is developed through careful and precise attention to details - nothing is glossed over or assumed. This shows an appreciation both for the underlying mathematics and for difficulties learners can face. Nothing is ever presented as "this is how it is done, just memorize the algorithm." For example, the development of the standard long-division algorithm in grade 5 is extremely well done, with great use of base-10 blocks, and constant references to the way "sharing" concepts were modeled in earlier lessons. Going through this helped me understand long-division better. :)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There should not be a trade-off between skill-mastery and creativity in mathematics. According to the JUMP philosophy, strong skills, factual knowledge, and confidence open up possibilities for creativity and risk-taking. They a pre-requisite for problem solving - you can't do higher-order work if you are mired in calculation difficulties and lack the confidence to experiment.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There are lots of informational/promotional videos about JUMP on their &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/user/JumpMath"&gt;youtube channel&lt;/a&gt;, and also an extended interview with &lt;a href="http://www.blogger.com/"&gt;&lt;span id="goog_1194416393"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;John Mighton&lt;span id="goog_1194416394"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href="http://www.tvo.org/TVOsites/WebObjects/TvoMicrosite.woa?video10458"&gt;TVO site&lt;/a&gt;.</content>
    <blogger:metaDescription/>
    <blogger:created>2011-06-06T17:20:21.076Z</blogger:created>
    <published>2011-06-07T14:52:00Z</published>
    <updated>2011-09-11T01:58:35.922Z</updated>
    <blogger:location/>
    <category scheme='tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5008879105295771159' term='math'/>
    <category scheme='tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5008879105295771159' term='education'/>
    <category scheme='tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5008879105295771159' term='school math'/>
    <category scheme='tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5008879105295771159' term='jump'/>
    <blogger:filename>/2011/06/jump-math.html</blogger:filename>
    <link/>
    <enclosure/>
    <blogger:trashed/>
  