<>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5008879105295771159.post-3294850593995422606</id>
    <blogger:type>POST</blogger:type>
    <blogger:status>LIVE</blogger:status>
    <author>
      <name>dan.mackinnon</name>
      <blogger:type>BLOGGER</blogger:type>
    </author>
    <title>of words and frogs</title>
    <content type='html'>&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiW4rWJym33mjkGvTWjjWfP8rV_NPLUK49gN8lVseCa067ONjxKRUBNW3Ystd3v0EWRGZ4gC762JQKUHKgoyLEz3Scr7Dnxguh7970JJuOPMVgLQAuos2ZxGXuuc6y0wcdA4RPIVxGb8WE/s1600/frogs2.PNG" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" data-original-height="429" data-original-width="477" height="179" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiW4rWJym33mjkGvTWjjWfP8rV_NPLUK49gN8lVseCa067ONjxKRUBNW3Ystd3v0EWRGZ4gC762JQKUHKgoyLEz3Scr7Dnxguh7970JJuOPMVgLQAuos2ZxGXuuc6y0wcdA4RPIVxGb8WE/s200/frogs2.PNG" width="200" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Inspired by Lillian Ho's article on using origami with adult ESL learners (see references below), I decided to build a lesson for high school ESL students around the &lt;a href="https://origamiusa.org/diagrams/jumping-frog"&gt;hopping frog&lt;/a&gt; model.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The basic activity went like this:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;
1. Students were shown how to fold the model without being given any verbal instructions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;
2. Students were given &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1ifsm7YeoiZFjwkeniPVeheEXOxovWjsQSc1e4UenXCE/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;a version of the instructions&lt;/a&gt; with all written instructions removed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;
3. In groups of 3 or 4, students were asked to provide written instructions on chart paper to go along with the diagrams.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;
4. The written instructions were shared by placing the chart papers up around the class, and students were asked to identify the important words that were used in the instructions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;
5. As a whole class, we folded the frog again, noting the mathematical ways we could describe each step.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEijQvJ35pneA-JQsDASs-E_Y4QQ_OKi4QBWTY6V10w747uiJ2lUfD5Y8QCQDQdK5BB8I9VFLYhrFZxipdR2MSRn0xWFmbJbcFg9PRtP1csLYlI0F4KX7dDeyCQp8uNpQsw_kxb1gvoIHNE/s1600/cut+instructions.PNG" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" data-original-height="334" data-original-width="922" height="115" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEijQvJ35pneA-JQsDASs-E_Y4QQ_OKi4QBWTY6V10w747uiJ2lUfD5Y8QCQDQdK5BB8I9VFLYhrFZxipdR2MSRn0xWFmbJbcFg9PRtP1csLYlI0F4KX7dDeyCQp8uNpQsw_kxb1gvoIHNE/s320/cut+instructions.PNG" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
If you try an activity along these lines, I expect that should be split over two or three sessions. We did step 1 at the end of another lesson, steps 2 and 3 on a second day, and steps 4 and 5 on a third day.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In thinking about the sort of descriptions that the students should be guided towards, it's helpful to note some of the observations provided in an article by Koichi Tateishi (see references): (1) the written words are not a replacement for the diagrams, but should be thought of as complementary, and (2) we should avoid technical origami terms (mountain fold, squash fold, etc.).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
When one group of students uncovered a useful word, it would get written up on the board for all groups to share, so as we went we developed a list of helpful words. With reference to the steps on the &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1ifsm7YeoiZFjwkeniPVeheEXOxovWjsQSc1e4UenXCE/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;instruction page&lt;/a&gt;, some words that the students used included or discussed at each step were:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;step 1&lt;/b&gt;: paper, card, square, rectangle, fold, half, long, short, side, middle, open, line;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;step 2&lt;/b&gt;: diagonal, top, side, edge;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;step 3&lt;/b&gt;: do again, repeat, other side;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;step 4&lt;/b&gt;: turn over, flip, corners, intersection, lines crossing;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;step 5&lt;/b&gt;: push, pinch, squash, together, peak;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;step 6&lt;/b&gt;: tip, up;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;step 7&lt;/b&gt;: center, in, inwards;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;step 8&lt;/b&gt;: flaps, outside, inside, arms;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;step 9&lt;/b&gt;: bottom, nose, legs;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;step 10&lt;/b&gt;: down, knees;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
These words were used in the context of providing instructions and directions - a very important type of speech act that students are routinely confronted with.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In the appendix to her article on the benefits of origami lessons for middle school students, Norma Boakes (see references below) provides a great sample mathematical dialog for the jumping frog model (step 5 of our lesson plan). Like Boakes suggests, in our mathematical discussion we talked about rectangles, squares, quadrilaterals, right angles, bisectors, 45 degree angles, triangles, pentagons, right-triangles, parallel and perpendicular lines. Each (now very familiar) step of the frog construction providing a concrete model for the concept we were talking about.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Through this lesson, we learned and reviewed a lot of everyday language around the giving and receiving of instructions that involve everyday spacial terms, and were also able to then apply a mathematical lens to deepen our understanding of what we were doing.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;References&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Boakes, N.J. (2009). "The Impact of Origami-Mathematics Lessons on Achievement and Spacial Ability of Middle-School Students." In Lang, R.J. (Ed) &lt;i&gt;Origami 4: Fourth International Meeting of Origami Science, Mathematics and Education&lt;/i&gt;. Natick, MA: A K Peters Ltd.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Ho, L.Y. (2002).&amp;nbsp; "Origami and the Adult ESL Learner." In Hull, T. (Ed.) &lt;i&gt;Origami 3: Third International Meeting of Origami Science, Mathematics and Education&lt;/i&gt;. Natick, MA: A K Peters Ltd.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tateishi, K. (2009). "Redundancy of Verbal Instructions in Origami Diagrams." In Lang, R.J. (Ed)&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Origami 4: Fourth International Meeting of Origami Science, Mathematics and Education&lt;/i&gt;. Natick, MA: A K Peters Ltd.</content>
    <blogger:metaDescription/>
    <blogger:created>2019-02-07T18:08:28.662Z</blogger:created>
    <published>2019-02-14T20:05:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-02-20T16:42:39.480Z</updated>
    <blogger:location/>
    <category/>
    <blogger:filename>/2019/02/of-words-and-frogs.html</blogger:filename>
    <link/>
    <enclosure/>
    <blogger:trashed/>
  