<>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5008879105295771159.post-7666416646647840212</id>
    <blogger:type>POST</blogger:type>
    <blogger:status>LIVE</blogger:status>
    <author>
      <name>dan.mackinnon</name>
      <blogger:type>BLOGGER</blogger:type>
    </author>
    <title>off-topic: progressive education in Ottawa</title>
    <content type='html'>If you know people in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottawa"&gt;Ottawa&lt;/a&gt; who care about public education, please let them know about an event that is coming up in support of &lt;a href="http://www.churchillalternative.ocdsb.ca/"&gt;Churchill Alternative School&lt;/a&gt;, and in support of alternative public education generally.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiLMr757WFiKBpUfg8Ium5A2e0zpdGJ9sNtzwFi8CrE_Fo2m7FcpF7ThQFwiKdJd9CadOizIkOFYdbTUcoi4CV_AuUp8nrGImMQbo1sR0pxEu_Bbdm1-tq4UCFxgoUzwxjUyMAMbkJT8Ok/s1600-h/alfiekohn.gif" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="400" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiLMr757WFiKBpUfg8Ium5A2e0zpdGJ9sNtzwFi8CrE_Fo2m7FcpF7ThQFwiKdJd9CadOizIkOFYdbTUcoi4CV_AuUp8nrGImMQbo1sR0pxEu_Bbdm1-tq4UCFxgoUzwxjUyMAMbkJT8Ok/s400/alfiekohn.gif" width="306" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
From the promotional literature about this public talk by &lt;a href="http://www.alfiekohn.org/index.php"&gt;Alfie Kohn&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
"Our knowledge of how children learn – and how schools can help -- has come a long way in the last few decades. Unfortunately, most schools have not: They’re still more about memorizing facts and practicing isolated skills than understanding ideas from the inside out; they still exclude students from any meaningful decision-making role; and they still rely on grades, tests, homework, lectures, worksheets, competition, punishments, and rewards. Alfie Kohn explores the alternatives to each of these conventional practices, explaining why progressive education isn’t just a realistic alternative but one that’s far more likely to help kids become critical thinkers and lifelong learners." &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Alfie Kohn is the author of eleven books, including Punished by Rewards, The Schools our Children Deserve, Unconditional Parenting, and, most recently, The Homework Myth. He has been described by Time magazine as America's “most outspoken critic of education’s fixation on grades [and] test scores.”  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The lecture will be on February 11th, 2010 from 7:00 to 9:30 pm at the auditorium of Woodroffe High School (2410 Georgina Dr., Ottawa). &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tickets are available online through &lt;a href="http://www.draregister.com/econnect/Activities/ActivitiesDetails.asp?ProcessWait=N&amp;amp;aid=1687"&gt;Dovercourt&lt;/a&gt; at a cost of $20 CDN each.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
If you are going to be in Ottawa on Feb 11 - please come out to hear Alfie's talk.</content>
    <blogger:metaDescription/>
    <blogger:created>2010-01-28T14:24:58.017Z</blogger:created>
    <published>2010-01-28T14:40:00Z</published>
    <updated>2011-09-11T02:01:08.046Z</updated>
    <blogger:location/>
    <category scheme='tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5008879105295771159' term='off-topic'/>
    <category scheme='tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-5008879105295771159' term='math'/>
    <blogger:filename>/2010/01/off-topic-progressive-education-in.html</blogger:filename>
    <link/>
    <enclosure/>
    <blogger:trashed/>
  